A Guide to the Henkel Family Papers, 1783-1916
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
The Henkel Family Papers 1783-1916
Special Collections, James Madison University
2065
The Henkel Collection consists of two Hollinger boxes and one flat box.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Placed on deposit at Carrier Library through the November, 1985 contract with the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society
Scope and Content Information
The Henkel Collection consists of two Hollinger boxes and one flat box, and spans a period from 1783 to 1916. The bulk of the collection consists of letters, religious documents, and newspapers and advertisements published by the Henkel Press. Also included are some Henkel family history materials and business documents, and miscellaneous secular materials.
The Henkel Press began as a crude printing press in the living room of Paul Henkel's house in New Market, Virginia, in 1806. Eventually, it published more Lutheran material than any other press in the country, and earned fame for its excellent children's books. Although the press began printing in German for the large Shenandoah Valley German community, it also published in English at an early date.
Many of the older letters in the Letters Series are in German while later ones are primarily in English. They demonstrate the dedication of the Henkel family to their faith as well as their activities within the Synod.
The Henkel Press Publications Series (including the Oversize Series) contains a large part of the collection, and includes handwritten drafts for advertisements to be printed, pamphlets, issues of Virginische Volksberichterand Westliche Correspondenz, and a formula for the ink used in printing.
Also in the collection (Secular Documents Series) are several handwritten school books, some with fraktur.
Organization
Partial organization by a previous researcher was maintained. Series are:
I. Letters.
II. Religious Documents.
III. Secular Documents.
IV. Family History.
V. Henkel Press Publications.
VI. Oversize: Henkel Press Publications; Miscellaneous
Bibliography
Edmonds, Albert Sydney. "The Henkels, Early Printers in New Market, Virginia," William and Mary Quarterly, 2nd series, v. 18, 1938.
Scheer, George F. "First Printing Press in the Valley of Virginia," Publishers' Weekly. Vol. 150, November 23, 1946.
Finck, Rev. William J. A Chronological Life of Paul Henkel. New Market, 1937. Xerox copy of typescript made by Richard R. Renalds, Timberville, VA., 1986. (SC BX8080.H42.C49 1986).
Contents List
- I: Letters. 1806-1892, and undated.
  - 1804-1820 (Box-folder 1:1)
    Mostly to Paul, Ambrose, and Socrates Henkel in German. Includes 1816 German diary with reference to Pt. Pleasant.
  - 1821-1892 (Box-folder 1:2)
    German and English. Numerous letters from N.C.
  - Undated (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Salyards, 1846-1891, and undated (Box-folder 1:4)
    Notes by J. Salyards; 1846 brochure on The New-Market Academy; unsigned poem; 2 copies 1875 Henkel pub. of review of "Idothea;" several items relating to Salyards Memorial Assn.
- II: Religious Documents 1783-1897 and undated
  - Service Literature undated. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Prayers; organization of service; responsive readings.
  - Sermons 1841-1897. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Most are titled and dated. Several in German. Includes Henkel list of subscribers for preaching, 1841-1852.
  - Music 1829 and undated (Box-folder 1:7)
    See also Oversize. Fragments of religious songbooks, some with notations.
  - Religious issues 1783-1889. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Writings from Bible; writings on religious ideas; treatise to Solomon from David Henkle, Lincolnton, NC, 1826.
  - Religious issues undated (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Marriage licenses 1825-1856. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Rockingham County licenses, some with notes that Ambrose or other Henkels performed ceremony.
  - Miscellaneous church papers 1813-1892 and undated (Box-folder 1:11)
    Includes book of miscellaneous accounts with members of Whitehaven congregation, 1813; mss. on worship services by 4 Valley Lutheran churches, called by Rev. Nischmucker in Woodstock Jan. 1828; minutes of church mtg., 1855; printed proceedings of extra session, Luth. Tennessee Synod, 1864.
- III: Secular Documents. 1790-1910, and undated
  - Prose and poetry, 1864 and undated (Box-folder 1:12)
    Includes a poem from a slave's point of view; a speech on American government and reason to vote Democratic; political qualifications of Henkel family.
  - Speeches, undated. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Four texts, one addressed to "Fellow Citizens of Shenandoah". Subjects are political and social concerns, incl. intemperance.
  - Business documents, 1790-1910. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Promises to pay, subscription orders, receipts, post office oath, a ledger book.
  - Spelling book identified as "Solon P.C. Henkel 1832." (Box-folder 2:1.5)
  - Schoolbooks. Undated (Box-folder 2:2-5)
    Handwritten in English. No documentation present to clarify the connection with the Henkel family. Folder 2, surveying; 3, navigation, with fractur; (Folder 4, mathematics, was withdrawn by the H-R Hist. Soc. on May 16, 2000); 5, word problems, with fractur. Folder 5 has on approx. page 6: "Tobias McGaughey."
- IV: Family history undated
  - Writings, newspaper clips, a few pictures on history of Henkel family and Press. (Box-folder 2:6)
- V: Henkel Press publications. 1806-1891.
  See also Oversize.
  - Miscellaneous printing drafts 1811-1817. (Box-folder 2:7)
    Handwritten horse advertisements, announcements of tannery shops; German and English.
  - Pamphlets 1806-1891. (Box-folder 2:8)
    Contains: St. Martin Luther's kleiner Katechismus... 1829 (58 cop.). Verhandlungen, Bericht der Verrichtungen, Auszug, or Report... evangelical Luthern Conference (North Carolina)... 1812; 1814; 1816; 1817 (2 cop.). Verrichtung der Special-Conferenze der Evang. Luth... in Virginia... 1806; 1807; 1808; 1809; 1815; 1831. Kurze Nachricht, Report, Bericht, or Minutes... Evang. Luth. Tennessee Synod... 1820, 1821, 1828, 1830, 1833, 1891.
  - Henkel Press publications. 1809-1868, and und., Oversize (Box Box 1)
  - Wool carding advertisements advertisements. 1809-1816., Handwritten drafts and printed (Box-folder Flat Box 1:1)
  - Miscellaneous announcements 1809-1858, 1879 and undated (Box-folder Flat Box 1:2)
    Includes sales and school notices, incl. one for S. Henkel's New Market Female Seminary; broadside advertising a "living quanacos;" price-setting resolution of Shenandoah Cty. carpenters, 1816; church raffle tickets.
  - Henkel Family Papers (Box-folder FLAT Box 1, con't.)
  - Music 1868 and undated (Box-folder Flat Box 1:3)
    Words to songs; includes ballad about St. Clair's defeat by Indians. Some probably not printed by Henkel Press.
  - Virginische Volksberichter und Neumarketer Wochenshrift, 1807-1809. Contains a 7 1/2 foot rolled list of subscribers, and the following issues: Dec. 23, 30, 1807. (Box-folder Flat Box 1:4-7)
  - Jan. 6, 20, 27; Feb. 3, 17; Mar. 2, 9, 16, 30, 1808. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - April 6, 13, 27 (partial copy); May 4, 11, 18, 25, 1808. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - June 8, 15, 22, 29; July 6, 13, 20, 27, 1808. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Aug. 10 (partial copy), 17, 31; Sept. 7, 1808. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Oct. 5 (1 1/2 copies), 12 (1 1/2 copies), 19 (partial copy), 26, 1808. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Nov. 2, 16 (2 copies), 23, 30; Dec. 7, 14, 1808. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Jan. 4, 11, 18 (partial), 1809. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Feb. 1, 8 (partial), 15, 22 (2 copies), 1809. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Mar. 1, 15, 22; Apr. 12, 19, 26, 1809. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - May 10, 24, 31; June 14, 1809. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Westliche Correspondenz, 1806-1822. (Box-folder Flat Box 1:8)
    Contains:
  - Apr. 12, 1806 (partial copy) (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Feb. 6, 1808. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Sept. 19, 1812. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - June 28, Aug. 2, 1822. (Box-folder Flat Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1782-1824, and undated Contains Rooster and Lion Henkel sheets, as well the following non-Henkel publications: 16 July 1782 issue of Philadelphische Correspondenz; unidentified sheet from 16 July 1808 German newspaper; 17 Jan. 1815 issue of Der Volksfreund (Lancaster PA); an 1824 election broadside in German; and 1889 pamphlet Die Vekehrung (Allentown, PA). (Box-folder Flat Box 1:9)
  - Contains a 1786 deed, a 1916 appointment for E.O. Henkel, part of a religious treatise, and 3 miscellaneous advertisements. (Box-folder Flat Box 1:10)